Hello everybody today's דף daf is ע"ז, Ayin Zayin, which we will,
in which we will God willing be beginning the next פרק, perek,
but we first have to finish up this one. So we pick
up on the משנה mishna on the middle of ע"ו עמוד ב'.
Ayin Vav amud bet.
We're still dealing with making various תנאים. tna'im. הרי זה גיטך אם
לא באתי מכאן ועד י"ב חודש.
Harei zeh gittech
im lo bati mikan ad yod bet chodesh. So we had mentioned
this a few times earlier. Here's your גט get if I don't
come from now with, if I don't return within twelve months.
ומת בתוך י"ב חודש, Umet bitoch yod bet chodesh, he died within
twelve months. אינו גט. Eino get. Now that they say what, what
do you mean אינו גט? eino get? He's not going to return
in twelve months. But he said אם לא באתי im lo bati
and without מהיום, mehayom, אם לא באתי im lo bati means when
I don't come. So by the time the גט get is supposed
to take effect, he's already dead. הרי זה גיטך מהיום אם לא
באתי מכאן ועד י"ב חודש, Harei zeh gittech mehayom im lo bati
mikan ad yod bet chodesh, as of now, if I don't return
within twelve months. ומת בתוך י"ב חודש, Umet bitoch yod bet chodesh,
and he died. So you know the תנאי tnai is going to
be fulfilled. הרי זה גט, Harei zeh get, it's a good גט.
get. אם לא באתי מכאן ועד י"ב חודש כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי.
Im lo bati mikan ad yod bet chodesh kitvu utnu get l'ishti.
Now if he says if I don't return within twelve months,
write and give a גט get to my wife. So again remember
אם im by itself means when, not just if. If and when.
In that case,
כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי. kitvu utnu get l'ishti. כתבו וחתמו בתוך י"ב
חודש, Kitvu v'chatmu bitoch yod bet chodesh, if they wrote it within
twelve months ונתנו אחר י"ב חודש v'natnu achar yod bet chodesh and
gave it afterwards, אינו גט, eino get, because this is showing you
that the תנאי tnai can go not only on the giving of
the גט get or on the effect of the גט get but
also on the writing of the גט. get. So he basically said
if and when I don't return, write a גט get for my
wife, and they wrote it too early. So that's not good, the
גט get is not valid. אינו גט. Eino get. כתבו ותנו גט
לאשתי
אם לא באתי מכאן ועד י"ב חודש. Kitvu utnu get l'ishti im
lo bati mikan ad yod bet chodesh. Let's say he reversed the
order and he said write and give a גט get to my
wife if I don't return, meaning if and when I don't return.
So the first פסק psak is it's the same. כתבו בתוך י"ב
חודש ונתנו אחר י"ב חודש אינו גט. Kitvu bitoch yod bet chodesh
v'natnu achar yod bet chodesh eino get. It's not good, as he
said only if and when I don't return and they wrote it
too early. But in this case רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer,
no, כזה גט, kazeh get, that would be valid. Why? Because as
we're going to see in the גמרא, Gemara, we're going to read
this statement that the כתבו kitvu is not yet the, is not
yet what's being made conditional. They're reading it with a big comma.
כתבו, Kitvu, comma, ותנו גט לאשתי אם לא באתי מכאן ועד י"ב
חודש. utnu get l'ishti im lo bati mikan ad yod bet chodesh.
So that's how רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is reading it. He's freeing
the כתבו kitvu because the phrase occurred before the תנאי. tnai. He's
freeing the כתבו kitvu from being conditional. כזה גט. Kazeh get. וכתבו
לאחר י"ב חודש ונתנו לאחר י"ב חודש U'kitvu l'achar yod bet chodesh
v'natnu l'achar yod bet chodesh and he says write it now but
give it after twelve months. ומת, Umet, and he died. אם הגט
קודם למיתה הרי זה גט, Im ha-get kodem l'misa harei zeh get,
if the גט get was given before he died, it's good. אם
מיתה קדמה לגט אינו גט, Im misa kadma l'get eino get, if
he died before it was given, it's not good. So far it's
all pretty obvious. אם אינו ידוע זהו שאמרו מגורשת ואינה מגורשת, Im
eino yadua zehu she'amru megureshet v'eina megureshet, if they don't know, she's
doubtfully divorced, which is of course the worst of both. Okay, the
last line seemed pretty obvious. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. תנא, Tana,
we taught a ברייתא Baraisa and we've seen this before as well.
רבותינו התירו להינשא. Raboseinu hitiru l'hinasei. Even when he says this is
your גט get if I don't come within twelve months and he
didn't say as of now, or אם im meaning if and when.
The
רבותינו, raboseinu, whoever our רבותינו, raboseinu, whoever they were, allowed her to
marry. Why is that? Why don't we say אם im means when
I don't come, it means at the end of twelve months, and
by then he's already dead? So the גמרא Gemara says מאן רבותינו,
man Raboseinu, who are these רבותינו? raboseinu? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל:
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: בי דינא דשרו משחא, beis dina de'sharu
mishcha, the בית דין beis din that permitted the oil of non-Jews.
That's the בית דין beis din of רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda
Nesiah, and the grandson of רבי יהודה נשיאה. Rabbi Yehuda Nesiah. They
were getting a little bit of a reputation about being an overly
lenient בית דין. beis din. Anyway, and now how are they allowing
this case? אם לא באתי. Im lo bati. How are they allowing
it to take to take effect early? סברי לה כרבי יוסי. Sabri
lah k'Rabbi Yossi. They hold like a רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, not
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi in our משנה mishna but a different רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi in בבא בתרא, Baba Basra, דאמר זמנו של שטר
מוכיח עליו. damar zmano shel shtar mochiach alav.
If a שטר shtar is dated, we say that it means that
it should take effect as of that date. He says that if
a שכיב מרע shechiv mera gives a גט, get, gives a שטר
מתנה shtar matana and it says like לאחר מיתה, achar misa, we
interpret it to mean מהיום ולאחר מיתה mehayom v'achar misa because of
the dating. So here too because of the dating in the גט,
get, even though in the גמרא Gemara raised differences before, here the
dating was written and the תנאי tnai was verbal, so maybe the
תנאי tnai overrides what's written. But nevertheless, we read them in conjunction
and we say the dating means as of now. אם לא באתי
Im lo bati is a תנאי. tnai. So he doesn't come within
twelve months, he dies or whatever, it takes effect as of now.
You don't just read אם לא באתי im lo bati by itself
to mean when, and then it's a גט לאחר מיתה. get l'achar
misa. You read it as a תנאי tnai because you have the
date in the גט get which means as of now. Okay, אמר
רבי אבא בריה דרבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן:
amar Rabbi Abba brei
d'Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan: רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda
Nesiah, so this רבותינו Raboseinu which he said was this בית דין
beis din that permitted oil, that's רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesiah,
בנו של רבן גמליאל, bno shel Rabban Gamliel, the son of רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, בר, bar, the son of who himself who was
the son of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda
Hanasi, meaning he's the grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi.
Okay, ולא הודו לו כל סיעתו, v'lo hodu lo kol siato, but
his חברה chevre there, his colleagues, did not agree to him about
this פסק psak of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. אמרי לה כל ימיו,
Amrei lah kol yamov, his entire life, no, he couldn't get anybody
to, he couldn't get people to agree to him. אמרי ליה רב
אלעזר, Amre leih Rav Elazar, so it sounds like we probably wouldn't
פסקן pasken that. There's a whole question about whether we do or
don't פסקן pasken like. Okay, if you take a look at the
תוספות, Tosafot, ולא הודו לו כל סיעתו, velo hodu lo kol siato,
תוספות Tosafot says אין להוכיח מכאן שאין הלכה כרבי יוסי. ein lehokiach
mikan she'ein halacha k'Rebbi Yosi. Even though it says that none of
his colleagues agreed with him, you can't prove that we don't say
that. Okay, that we don't פסקן pasken that way. אף על גב
דרב פסק כוותיה af al gav deRav paskak vateih משום דרבי יוחנן
קאמר הכא לא הודו לו כל סיעתו mishum deRebbi Yochanan ka'amar hacha
lo hodu lo kol siato ורב ורבי
יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוחנן. v'Rav v'Rebbi Yochanan halacha k'Rebbi Yochanan. We should
go like רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says that
his colleagues didn't agree with him, which sounds like we don't פסקן
pasken like him, so does that mean we don't פסקן pasken like
רבי יוסי? Rebbi Yosi? So he says you can't prove it that
way. Why? דהוה רבי יוחנן גופיה יכול לסבור כרבי יוסי. dehavah Rebbi
Yochanan gufiah yachol lisbor k'Rebbi Yosi. How do you know what רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan himself פסקנס? paskens? Maybe רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan also
פסקנס paskens like him. He's just telling you a historical fact that
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi couldn't get his colleagues to agree with him.
או שמא דוקא הכא דעל פה לא סבר ליה כרבי יוסי, o
shema davka hacha de'al peh lo savar leih k'Rebbi Yosi, or maybe
you don't hold like רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi when the date is
in the document and the תנאי tnai is verbal, external to the
document. But maybe if you have the date and the תנאי tnai
in the document, maybe you would go like רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi
that זמנו של שטר מוכיח עליו. zmano shel shtar mochiach alav. Okay,
so there still remains a big question if we rule like רבי
יוסי Rebbi Yosi by זמנו של שטר zmano shel shtar or זמנו
של גט מוכיח עליו. zmano shel get mochiach alav. Okay, now back
to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi though couldn't
get his colleagues to agree with him. אמרי ליה רב אלעזר לההוא
סבא. Amre leih Rav Elazar lehahu saba. רב אלעזר Rav Elazar said
to a certain elder who was part of that בית דין beis
din of רבי יהודה נשיאה Rebbi Yehuda Nesi'ah who ruled like רבי
יוסי. Rebbi Yosi. So כי שריתיה, ki shariteih, when you permitted this
woman, when he said אם לא באתי im lo bati but you
added the date to the document, so you read it as מעכשיו
אם לא באתי, me'achshav im lo bati, and you permitted this woman
when the husband died. So לאלתר שריתיה, le'alter shariteih, do you permit
her to get married right away? Because once the guy's dead, you
know that the תנאי tnai is going to be satisfied, right? As
long as it means, as long as it means מעכשיו, me'achshav,
okay, whether you said it explicitly or because of זמנו של שטר,
zmano shel shtar, you know that the תנאי tnai is going to
be satisfied. So do you let her get married right away? או
לאחר שנים עשר חודש שריתיה, o l'achar shneim asar chodesh shariteih, or
do you only let her get married after twelve months, after it's
like the time, you know,
the תנאי tnai is actually fulfilled, not just you know it's going
to be fulfilled. So the גמרא Gemara
says לאלתר שריתיה, le'alter shariteih, do you permit her right away, דהא
לא אתי, deha lo ati, you know he's not going to come,
או לאחר שנים עשר חודש שריתיה, o l'achar shneim asar chodesh shariteih,
do you only do it after
twelve
months, דהא איקיים תנאה, deha ikayaim tna'ah, because that's the time where
the תנאי tnai is actually fulfilled in practice. So the גמרא Gemara
says
תבעי ליה למתניתין, tibay leih l'matnitin, why are you only asking for
one of the people that was part of that בית דין beis
din that ruled like רבי יוסי? Rebbi Yosi? This is a question
even on our משנה. Mishnah. That was only a question if he
just said אם לא באתי im lo bati without the מעכשיו. me'achshav.
But it's a question you can ask that question about רבי יוסי.
Rebbi Yosi. But the question about when to permit to marry can
be asked even according to the משנה Mishnah if you did say
מעכשיו. me'achshav. The משנה Mishnah says מעכשיו אם לא באתי מכאן ועד
שנים עשר חודש ומת בתוך שנים עשר חודש הרי זה גט. me'achshav
im lo bati mikan v'ad shneim asar chodesh umet betoch shneim asar
chodesh harei zeh get. So he said as of now within twelve
months and he died immediately, so you know it's going to be
fulfilled, so and he said as of now, so you know it's
going to be a good
גט. get. לאלתר הוי, le'alter havei, can she get married right away,
דהא
לא אתי, deha lo ati, he's not going to come, או דילמא
לאחר שנים עשר חודש, o dilma l'achar shneim asar chodesh, or maybe
you wait till twelve months דאיקיים תנאיה, de'ikayaim tna'iah, that's when the
תנאי tnai is fulfilled. So why didn't you ask that on the
משנה? Mishnah? גמרא Gemara says אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, you're
right, I could have asked it on the משנה, Mishnah, but משום
דהוי במעשה, mishum dehavah b'ma'aseh, since that elder was part of that
בית דין beis din and they were פסקנינג paskening למעשה, l'ma'aseh, right?
If I asked it on the משנה, Mishnah, I'm just asking like
a hypothetical question: Oh, the משנה Mishnah gives this ruling, I wonder
according to the משנה Mishnah when she would be able to get
married, right away, after twelve months. But somebody was part of a
בית דין beis din that actually ruled this way in practice. So
that בית דין beis din probably thought through the parameters and thought
through under what conditions would they let her get married. Would it
be right away, would it be after twelve months? So I wanted
to ask somebody who was part of that בית דין, beis din,
maybe I'd get a more concrete answer than just speculating on the
question. Okay, by the way, the גמרא Gemara does not give an
answer to that. What is the story, right away or after twelve
months? It's not clear anyway why she should have to wait twelve
months. So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot
says דאיקיים תנאה. de'ikayaim tna'ah. תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר לאלתר מאי
יש לחוש. v'im tomar le'alter mai yesh lachosh.
I don't understand why can't she get married right away? Why do
you have to wait? What's the סברא? sevara? דהודאי יתקיים תנאי דכיון
דמת לא ישוב עד לביתו, d'havadai itkayaim tnai d'keivan demet lo yashuv
od l'veito, he won't return. ויש לומר דאיכא למגזר אטו לא מת,
v'yesh lomar d'ika lemigzar atu lo met, כי אין העולם יודעים שמת.
ki ein ha'olam yod'im shemet.
People heard you made a condition, if he doesn't return in twelve
months, and then they see you're getting married a month later. So
they say wait a minute, we heard that he gave the condition
if he doesn't return in twelve months. So people only have partial
information and therefore the impression is that you don't have to wait
in general for the תנאי tnai to be fulfilled. So תוספות Tosafot
says the question here is like a גזירה gezeirah type of an
issue or an appearance type of an issue. One wonders if one
should also say this in a more fundamental way, like how תנאים
tna'im work? Right? Maybe the mechanism still is that when the תנאי
tnai is fulfilled, that triggers the effect of the גט get retroactively,
right? So even if you know it will be fulfilled, but maybe
somehow it's a trigger mechanism and you still need it in order
to effect the, you know. So the the taking effect of the
גט. get. So תוספות Tosafot doesn't seem to think that's true, and
תוספות Tosafot makes it a question of appearances, yes.
And deciding that a conditional תנאי tnai would be
a conditional גט get with a תנאי tnai would be more publicized
than someone's death.
Yeah, I agree. Okay, I don't know what to say about that.
Okay, now, by the way, another interesting thing just as parenthetical, the
word על אתר al atar which means right away, I think I
mentioned this before, but it is actually a conjunction of two words
which is על אתר al atar,
which means like, well על al should be with an א. alef.
But anyway, אתר atar means the place. Like, you know, right on
this place. Like it's sort of like the point about מכאן, mikan,
like we had yesterday. מכאן ועד יב חודש, mikan v'ad yud bet
chodesh, מכאן mikan literally means as a geographical thing, you know, this
place, but it means as of now. For על אתר, al atar,
right, when the guy died on the spot, right, he died right
there, immediately. Okay, or we'd better get married על al אתר, atar
right then and there. Okay, אמר אביי, amar Abbaye, הכל מודים hakol
modim היכא דאמר לכשתצא חמה מנרתיקה. heicha d'amar lich'she'tetzei chama min hartika.
So now he's just going to frame again the position of רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi about זמנו של שטר מוכיח עליו zmano shel shtar
mochiach alav in a case where actually it's pretty clear but he
just uses this as an example. Everybody agrees that if the guy
says, this is your גט get when the sun goes out of
its, you know, of its like cloak, of its sheathing, of its
right, of its box, meaning when sunrise. So לכשנפקא lich'she'nafpka קאמר לה,
ka'amar lah, it means when it rises.
ובכי מיית בליליא uv'chi mayit b'leilya if he died in the night,
so הוי גט לאחר מיתה, havei get l'achar mita, it's a גט
לאחר מיתה get l'achar mita because he said when the sun rises
and at that stage he's already dead. Okay, if he says
על מנת al m'nat שתיצא חמה מנרתיקה she'tetzei chama min hartika on
condition that the sun rises, מעכשיו קאמר לה, me'achshav ka'amar lah, it
means as of now on the condition that. דאמר d'amar על מנת
al m'nat clearly means as of now. דאמר רב הונא אמר
רב, d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav, ואמר רב, v'amar Rav, שצריך להיות
רבי, she'tzarich lihyot Rebbe, right? כל האומר על מנת כאומר מעכשיו דמי.
kol ha'omer al m'nat k'omer me'achshav dami. If you say על מנת
al m'nat it's like you say מעכשיו. me'achshav. So if he says
לכש lich'she it means when. If he says על מנת al m'nat
it means as of now on the condition that. The debate of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi about when do you use the זמן zman
to combine with something, meaning that's only when you said אם. im.
Okay.
לא נחלקו אלא באם, lo nechelku ela b'im, אם, im, תצא. tetzei.
מר סבר לה כרבי יוסי, mar savar lah k'Rabbi Yosi, one position
is like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, דאמר זמנו של שטר מוכיח עליו.
d'amar zmano shel shtar mochiach alav. So you have the date of
the document and the date plus אם, im, the אם im becomes
the condition. אם im means
if. Okay. ובעינא מהיום אם מתי, uv'aina me'hayom im mati, מעכשיו אם
מתי, me'achshav im mati, and then it'll take effect even if he
died in the middle of the night because it means as of
now. ומר לא סבר לה כרבי יוסי, u'mar lo savar lah k'Rabbi
Yosi, the other one doesn't hold like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, והוי
ליה כאם מתי גרידא, v'havei lei k'im mati greida, and it's just
אם מתי im mati and אם מתי im mati by itself means
אם תצא חמה im tetzei chama means when, if there's no date,
if there's no מעכשיו, me'achshav, it means when, and then it would
be a case of when the sun rises and it would be
a גט לאחר מיתה. get l'achar mita. Now by the way תוספות
Tosafot says that according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi even if you
said לכשתצא, lich'she'tetzei, but if you combine that with the זמנו של
שטר, zmano shel shtar, you have מהיום לכשתצא, me'hayom lich'she'tetzei, and that's
a case of a ספק גט. safek get. Okay, but anyway, the
basic point is everybody agrees when you say לכש lich'she it means
when. Everybody agrees that when you say, when you say you know,
when you say אם im and even if you add זמנו של
שטר zmano shel shtar the best you'll get to is a ספק
מגורשת. safek megureshet. Everybody agrees when you say על מנת al m'nat
it means מהיום על מנת me'hayom al m'nat and that it would
be good even without זמנו של שטר. zmano shel shtar. The basic
debate is אם. im. אם im without זמנו של שטר zmano shel
shtar means when and אם im with זמנו של שטר zmano shel
shtar means if and that's the basic date of רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. Now by the way the same question, if you said על
מנת al m'nat if the sun rises, you could have the question
can she get married now, does she have to wait till the
sun rises? Like the גמרא, Gemara, well that was the גמרא's Gemara's
question before when the guy dies, so you know it's going to
be fulfilled, but maybe here anyway you can quote Hume and say
we don't know if the sun's going to rise tomorrow just because
it's risen every every other last day for the last ten million
years is no evidence, right? That's Hume's point, wasn't that Hume's point?
Right? The fact that something occurred a million times in the past
does not mean is no evidence that it's going to happen the
same way tomorrow. Yes. Okay, yes, Charlie.
Yes, so רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi's point is that the date of
the גט get determines its date of validity. Yes. This is actually
a problem here because whether she divorced at night or during the
day, the date in the גט get is going to be the
same.
Oh, that's
actually, you know what, that's interesting, that would explain רש"י Rashi because
רש"י Rashi says when you say לכשתצא lich'she'tetzei
it's definitely a case of a גט לאחר מיתה get l'achar mita
and תוספות Tosafot says why is that, why isn't it מהיום לאחר
מיתה me'hayom l'achar mita
right? Because you have the date. So maybe what you're saying is
right, maybe if you give it to her at night and he
dies in the middle of the night, then you can't have the
the date can't be מעכשיו me'achshav because maybe the date means later
in that day, not earlier in that day. There was an earlier
תוספות Tosafot that asked that question essentially, is when if you have
the זמן... zman... or even if a guy said מהיום mehayom and
he didn't say מעכשיו, me'achshav, does מהיום mehayom mean as of this
minute or does he mean as of today and exactly raising questions
like that. So that's an interesting point. So maybe according to רש"י
Rashi it doesn't mean as of this minute even according to רבי
יוסי. Rebbe Yosi. So that's why the date plus לשיטתיה lashitateih if
it's all the same date would be לאחר מיתה. l'achar misa. It's
a good point. Okay. So let's take a look now as this
פרק perek continues. A lot of coughing going on. Okay. It says
כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי אם לא באתי מכאן ועד שנים עשר חודש.
kisvu u'snu get l'ishti im lo bati mikan v'ad shneim asar chodesh.
So if he says write and give it if I don't come.
So there רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi says that we chop off the
כתבו, kisvu, we say write it right now and give it if
I don't come. Haven't we had this before? No, we did not
skip it. אמר ליה רב יימר לרב אשי, amar leih Rav Yemar
l'Rav Ashi, לימא קסבר רבי יוסי כתב גט על תנאי כשר, leima
kasavar Rebbe Yosi ksav get al tnai kosher, meaning he assumes that
maybe when רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi says if you wrote it before
the twelve months, maybe רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi is disagreeing with both
parts of the משנה mishna and saying that you can make the
giving of the גט get conditional or you can make a תנאי,
tnai, but maybe the writing of the גט get is something that
you can't make conditional which would be interesting. But again, that gets
to the point that we've been assuming from the beginning and part
of this might have to do with רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer and
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir whether it's עדי כתיבה כרתי edei ksiva karsi
or עדי חתימה כרתי. edei chasima karsi. But that the giving of
the גט—how get much is the giving of the גט get something
that the סופר sofer does and how much is it something that
fundamentally the בעל ba'al is doing through the סופר? sofer? So the
גמרא Gemara asks what's going on there? Could we not do that
right now please? Thank you. So
if the writing of the גט get is something that the בעל
ba'al is doing through the סופר, sofer, you should be able to
make it conditional just like everything else. But if the writing of
the גט get maybe is fundamentally something the סופר sofer is doing,
maybe he needs the בעל's ba'al authorization, but maybe it's fundamentally something
the סופר sofer is doing, maybe you can't make it על תנאי,
al tnai, right? So that's what the גמרא Gemara thinks maybe according
to רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yosi. Maybe רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi is saying
that you can't make the writing on a תנאי, tnai, you can
make the giving on a תנאי, tnai, but not the writing on
a תנאי. tnai. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא קסבר רבי יוסי
כתב גט על תנאי כשר? leima kasavar Rebbe Yosi ksav get al
tnai kosher? לא, lo, לעולם אימא לך פסול. le'olam eima lach pasul.
No,
he agrees you can make a תנאי tnai on the writing. ושאני
הכא, v'shani hacha, and
the only case he agrees with is to say if I, when
I don't come, write it, then it wouldn't be good if you
wrote it early. But he says write it and give it when
I don't come. In that case we chop off the "write it"
from the "give it when I don't come." He says מידי דהוה
ליה למימר אם לא באתי כתבו ותנו, midi d'hava leih l'meimar im
lo bati kisvu u'snu, he could have said if and when I
don't come, write it and give it, so clearly the condition would
be going on both parts of the statement. And instead he said
כתבו ותנו אם לא באתי, kisvu u'snu im lo bati, write it
and give it if I don't come, if and when I don't
come. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what he meant or this
is what we're going to say he meant: כתבו מאכשיו, kisvu me'achshav,
write it as of now, ותנו אם לא באתי, u'snu im lo
bati, okay, and give it, so the condition only goes on the
most proximate verb. Okay. It doesn't go on both of the verbs.
ורבנן, v'rabbanan, and the Rabbis say, לא שנא
הכי ולא שנא הכי. lo shna hacha v'lo shna hacha.
It doesn't matter either way. Can I help you?
Yeah, what about RJC? What time are we supposed to be there?
8:30. 8:30.
There's also a few blocks away here.
I have no idea where the RJC is. Okay. Okay. תנו רבנן.
tanu rabbanan. Our Rabbis taught: לאחר שבוע. l'achar shavua.
Now if somebody says here's the גט get and it'll take place
לאחר שבוע, l'achar shavua, after the שבוע, shavua, which means after the
seven-year cycle, when שמיטה shmitta is over. After. Now how soon after?
Immediately after? That's going to be the question. So the answer's going
to be שנה. shana. It actually takes place only one year later.
Okay? Somehow after means not immediately after. It's a funny read, okay?
This will take place after the שמיטה shmitta is over. After it's
over means a year after it's over. We do like one unit;
it's made up of seven years. לאחר שנה. l'achar shana. This will
take place after the after after this year. Not at the end
of this year. Like you know after this year it'll take effect.
So how long after? חודש. chodesh. So okay, if you're talking about
the secular year and you give somebody something in 2016, you say
this will take effect after this year, it takes effect in February
2017. Which is a strange thing. Why don't we interpret it to
mean immediately after? Okay. לאחר חודש. l'achar chodesh. It'll take effect after
the month. שבת. Shabbos. It's a week after the month. לאחר שבת.
l'achar Shabbos. This will take effect after שבת. Shabbos. So here there's
already a discussion. מאי? mai? One day later? Okay. That's what you
would have thought, of course. דרש רב זירא קמיה דרב אסי ואמרי
לה רב אסי קמיה דרב יוחנן וקאמר: darash Rav Zeira kamei d'Rav
Assi v'amri lah Rav Assi kamei d'Rav Yochanan v'ka'amar:
חד בשבא ותרי ותלת, chad b'shabba v'trei v'tlat, Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, בתר
שבתא, batar Shabbos, that's still connected to the previous שבת. Shabbos. So
it's not like "after." It's right, you could still make הבדלה havdala
then. If that half of the week is still שייך shayach to
the—it's not "after." That's still somehow in the ambit, you know, in
the shadow of the previous שבת. Shabbos. That seems to be the
idea. "After" doesn't mean immediately after. It means, you know, after you're
fully away from. So what's fully away from? So to be, you
know, as long while you're still like if you think back to
the year, about the month after the year, right? I think that
like the first month after the new year, if you're in January,
you're still writing checks from the old year. Right. If you still
write checks with... wrong date, they're מוחל, mochel, they understand, right? So
you have to be. I think so, I think yeah, I think
banks will take it if it has the wrong date with if
it's if it's a little while after the New Year. So anyway,
so after he's understood to mean you're fully away from. So how
out of שבת Shabbos is fully away of שבת? Shabbos? Not one
day maybe another, you're still in the afterglow of שבת. Shabbos. So
Sunday, Monday, and Tuesday בתר שבתא. Basar Shabsa. ארבע חמשא ומעלי שבתא,
Arba Chamshav Ma'ali Shabsa, but Wednesday, Thursday, Friday קמי שבתא, Kami Shabsa,
that's connected to the coming שבת. Shabbos. Okay, which I guess means
if somebody says here's here's your גט get and it'll take effect
before שבת, Shabbos, maybe it takes effect on Wednesday. Okay, anyway, תניא,
Tanya, רבי אומר: Rebbe omer: לאחר הרגל שלושים יום. l'achar haregel shloshim
yom. If you said this'll take effect after יום טוב Yom Tov
is over, after יום טוב, Yom Tov, it means thirty days after
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, that's a big impact of יום טוב
Yom Tov on a whole thirty days. נפק רבי חייא דרשה משמיה
דרבי. Nafak Rebbe Chiya darsha mishme deRebbe. רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya went
out and you know taught this teaching in the name of רבי,
Rebbe, וקילסוהו, ve-kilsueh, and he was praised. משמיה דרבים, mishme deRabbim, then
he taught it in the name of like the majority opinion, ולא
קילסוהו, belo kilsueh, people didn't praise him because it's a דעת יחיד,
das yachid, don't go ahead and teach it as if it's a
consensus. אמר ליה שכחה כוותיה, Amlei sikhu'ach kevasah, you don't rule that
way. It doesn't tell you how long after the רגל, regel, but
it's not a full month. Okay, הדרן לך מי שאחזו. hadran lach
Mi she-achazo. Yes.
So this is two instances in this סוגיא sugya where we have
a rabbi not being accepted apparently.
What do you mean?
I mean this instance, not
the early רבי, Rebbe, it's so interesting the earlier example was despite
historical facts, you can't learn whether that's the הלכה. halacha.
You mean about רב יוסי Reb Yose's colleagues not agreeing with him.
And here you've got רבי Rebbe historical
facts that obviously impact how you should learn.
Right. Right, that's an interesting point.
And what did we say?
Did we say שמעתא שכיחא לאו? shmatta shechicha lav? I would have
to look, I cannot tell you the answer off the top of
my head. Okay, נו פרק, nu perek, we are now moving away
from
שליחות shlichus and תנאים, tna'im, right? I mean in a way the
whole פרק perek we began with so much about שליחות, shlichus, okay,
but then we got into all this interesting discussions about תנאים tna'im
and how to parse them and whether you need תנאי כפול tnai
kaful etc. And now we're going to something we really haven't addressed
almost at all, which is the question about the act of giving
the גט, get, okay. So let's take a look.
In chapter eight.
הזורק גט לאשתו, Hazorek get l'ishto,
a man throws a גט get to his wife. והיא בתוך ביתה,
ve-hi betoch beisah,
she's in her house, או בתוך חצרה, o betoch chatzerah, her yard,
הרי זו מגורשת, harei zu megureshes,
she's divorced, because it's put in her property. Okay. Once it lands.
No, no, no, once it lands. I don't know, let's not go
there right now. זרקו לה בתוך ביתו או בתוך חצרו, Zarko lah
betoch beiso o betoch chatzero, let's say he gave it to her
or threw it to her and they're standing in his house, okay,
or his yard. אפילו היא עמו במיטה, afillu hi imo bamittah, or
they're lying together in bed. I don't know what the 'even' is,
that would you would say is less a sense of separation than
the other cases, anyway, אינה מגורשת, eino megureshes, she's not divorced.
But wait she didn't get it?
Ah, so it sounds like it like landed by her feet, okay,
it landed alright guys,
people behave. It sounds like it landed by her feet and therefore
she's not because it's not her property. However, לתוך חיקה betoch cheikah
או לתוך קלתה, o betoch kaltah, if it was on her person,
okay, her חיק cheik is either her lap or bosom, it fell
onto her body, or her קלתה kaltah which is like a basket,
a purse, הרי זו מגורשת. harei zu megureshes. Now the person's interesting,
one thing to say on her person, even if she's in her
husband's domain it was put on her person, it's another interesting question
about whether it's on her like an object that she owns but
is an object where is that object? Is she holding that object?
Right. Is it on the floor? Good question, so we're going to
see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Now the big conceptual question
here
is how much by the idea of גט, get, ונתן בידה, ve-natan
beyadah, is it an idea of a קנין kinyan of transferring it
in a way although it's בעל כרחה, bal korchah, she could refuse,
but transferring it in a way that part of the act is
seen as giving her possession of it and therefore it has to
be a type of a transfer that normally would lead to the
taking of possession of an object? Or meaning the ownership? Or how
much is it just the physical act of giving it to her?
Okay. So for example there was a whole interesting discussion in the
גמרא Gemara before if it's written on איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, you
can give a גט get on something that can't that is
forbidden to derive benefit from. Now according to some opinions, there's no
way you can even possess something that's forbidden to derive benefit from.
You can physically hand it to somebody, but it could be that
it can't be possessed as a matter of owning it, right, because
maybe that's its very nature is considered to be outside of the
ability to be owned. Anyway, so that's like the conceptual question we're
going to be dealing with here, is that how much is it
an issue of ownership and how much is it an issue of
just take of like giving it physically giving it to her.
What's that called physically giving it to somebody?
The language in the אחרונים acharonim is most is it a דין
din of a מעשה נתינה, ma'aseh nesinah, נתינה, netinah, or is it
just as or is it a קנין? kinyan? Okay. So is it
just the act of giving or is it the act an action
of taking possession. Now you can force her to take possession. בעל
כרחה be-al korcha maybe, but halachically it has to be defined, it
has to have the parameters of what an act of קנין kinyan
would be. Okay, so something for example, that's what the a good
test case might be איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. If you say you
can't do קנין kinyan on איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah but you could
do a giving a גט get on איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, except
some people say you can do קנין kinyan on איסורי הנאה, issurei
hana'ah, so it doesn't prove it one way or the other. Okay,
but that's the conceptual question here. Yes.
So the other question about the purse would be then כליו של
מוכר ברשות לוקח. kelav shel mocher bi'reshus lokeach.
That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to deal with exactly. Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מנלן מילי, minalan
milli,
where do you get this from? דתנו רבנן, detanu rabanan, our rabbis
taught: ונתן בידה venasan beyadah by the גט, get, and he shall
give it in her hand. אין לי אלא ידה, ein li ela
yadah, I only know her hand. גגה חצרה וקרפיפה מניין? gagah chatzerah
ve'karfipah minayin? How do I know her roof, her yard, and her
little- what's קרפיף? karfif? It's like a
portico or something, whatever it is. מניין? minayin? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar:
ונתן מכל מקום. venasan mikol makom. So what exactly the דרשא derasha
is is not so clear. What do you mean ונתן מכל מקום?
venasan mikol makom? The next word is בידה. beyadah. Anyway, okay, but
anyway whatever it is, it's a דרשא derasha that רש"י Rashi says
because it could have said בידה יתננה. beyadah yitnenah. So saying ונתן
בידה venasan beyadah allows ונתן venasan to be דרש darshed a little
bit independent of בידה. beyadah. דתניא נמי הכי גבי גנב, detanya nami
hachi gabi ganav, we taught by a גנב. ganav. ידו, yado, it
says: אם המצא תמצא בידו הגניבה משור עד חמור עד שה חיים
שנים ישלם. im himatzei timatzei beyado hageneivah mishor ad chamor ad seh
chayim shenayim yeshalem. If it's in his hand, the גניבה, geneivah, which
means that he's taken possession of it. אין לי אלא ידו, ein
li ela yado, I only know his hand. גגו חצירו וקרפיפו מניין?
gago chatzeiro ve'karfipo minayin? How do I know if it's on his
property? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: המצא תמצא מכל מקום. himatzei timatzei mikol
makom. Now רש"י Rashi by the way says the חידוש chiddush here
is
is that if he actually like took your cow and stole your
cow and brought it to his property, you don't need a דרשא
derasha of המצא תמצא. himatzei timatzei. It's in his hands because he
did an act of- his property- you said brought
it to your property?
His property I mean. Okay, you don't need המצא תמצא himatzei timatzei
because it's in his hands because he did an act of possession.
He took your cow and he did משיכה meshichah on it or
he took your wallet and he lifted it up. Okay, what you
need it for is, let's say your cow wandered into his yard,
and he decided, "I'm not returning that cow," and he locked the
door to do some act to possess it but he did not
do משיכה, meshichah, he didn't do anything, he basically just had his
intent and somehow some type of an act not done directly to
the object. Okay, and that is a חידוש. chiddush. Why? You mean
just locking the door is considered a מעשה גניבה? ma'aseh geneivah? So
that's the חידוש, chiddush, like, let's say it fell into his hand.
Let's say, you know, I don't know, you threw a baseball and
somebody was playing catch and they threw a baseball and it fell
into his lap and he said, "Hey mister, could you return our
ball?" And he said, "No." So would that be an act of
גניבה geneivah right there? Right? So it just- so you didn't directly
do an act, but it was on your person, on your property,
and you wanted to possess it. Okay, so that's what רש"י Rashi
says the חידוש chiddush here is that that constitutes an act of
גניבה. geneivah.
רש"י Rashi says, I
think
it's
the רש"י Rashi coming up, one minute. One minute, let me- מדלא
כתיב בידו הודן. midla kesiv beyado hodan.
Yeah, I think it's coming up. We'll see it, I'll point it
out to you when it comes up. Okay, so anyway the גמרא
Gemara says like this:
וצריכא, u'tzricha, you need to tell me both by גט get and
by גנב. ganav. דאי אשמעינן גט משום דבעל כרחה מגרשה. de'i ashmeinan
get mishum de'be'al korcha megarshah.
You can do it against her will. So that means that maybe,
you know, the husband has more power and we'll consider more things
to be an act of giving the גט. get. Or if you
want to get back to the way I framed the question earlier,
maybe it's more of an act of giving than an act of
taking possession, and therefore that's considered that it was given to her
even if it might not be considered a way of her to
take possession.
אבל גנב דלאו בעל כרחו. aval ganav delav be'al korcho. Ganav which
is not against his will- not against the גנב's ganav will?
In your will?
Yeah, that's true exactly. Maybe being in his yard is not an
act of גניבה. geneivah. So that's a חידוש. chiddush. ואשמעינן גנב משום
דקנסיה רחמנא. v'ashmeinan ganav mishum de'kansyei rachmana. If it's a גנב ganav
and it is an act of גניבה, geneivah, that's because he did
something wrong, so the תורה Torah is more prepared to look at
it as an act of גניבה. geneivah.
אבל גט אימא לא, aval get eima lo, but גט get maybe
it's a narrower definition, צריכא tzricha you need both cases.
Why would it depend, like, you know, let's say Hillel, Shammai, how
you allowed to divorce somebody and then, you know, if it's not
ערוות דבר ervas davar and...
Yeah, maybe. All right, fine, the גמרא Gemara just needs some basis
to distinguish. Okay, and anyway take a look at רש"י, Rashi, okay.
אימא, eima, רש"י Rashi says- this is the רש"י Rashi I was
referring to before,
רש"י: Rashi: אבל גנב דלא מחייב אלא מדעתו, aval ganav d'lo mechayiv
ela mi'da'ato, he wouldn't be חייב chayav if it was against his
will. אימא מדעתו נמי לא תקני ליה חצירו, eima mi'da'ato nami lo
tikni leh chatzeiro, maybe he doesn't take possession even if he does
it willingly. What would that mean? אם לא משך, im lo mashach,
if he didn't do משיכה. meshichah. כגון נכנסה לחצירו ונעל בפניה, kegon
nichnesah l'chatzeiro ve'na'al befaneha, maybe that would not be enough. So the
חידוש chiddush is that that is enough, even if you didn't actually
do an act to the thing, you just closed your gate, you
at least have to close your gate. One wonders in a case
where it fell into your hand, you have to close your hand?
Or is just the intent not to give it back enough? But
anyway, but the point is nevertheless there was a- you were much
more passive, nevertheless that's an act of גניבה. geneivah. Okay? Now again,
you know, you could ask a similar question by a גנב. ganav.
A גנב ganav isn't legitimately taking possession although we talk about קנייני
גניבה, kinyanei geneivah, but is there an act of קנין kinyan by
a גנב? ganav? Or... Or is it an act of just taking
it away from you? Do you define what makes somebody a גנב
ganav to be the exactly same conditions of what possession would be
defined of in normal cases of קניין? kinyan? Okay, so it's a
similar question you could ask by גט. get. Although by גנב ganav
because the emphasis is still about your possession, my possession, I'm trying
to bring it into my possession, we normally do assume that the
definitions are much more classic קניין kinyan definitions. But by גט, get,
it still remains somewhat of an open question. Now let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with it. Okay, so that's the basic first
סוגיא. sukya.
חצירה, Chatzeira, now the גמרא Gemara says you put it in her
yard, I don't get it says the גמרא, Gemara, מה שקנתה אשה
קנה בעלה. Ma shekanta isha kanta ba'alah. What the woman owns, the
husband owns. So anything if a מציאה metzia would fall into her
yard, it would go to her husband. So if the גט get
falls into yard, it's now owned by the husband. Now this presumably,
now there's two ways to frame this question. The way I just
framed it says that we are talking about
קניין. kinyan. I don't care that you gave it onto her person
or property. It should automatically ownership automatically transferred to the husband. But
you could ask that even if you put it on her person?
Ownership transfers to the husband. But if you were to frame the
question that way, okay, then and there's a way maybe you could
distinguish the cases, but if you frame the question that the ownership
of an object that goes on her property transfers to the husband,
then it means that we're seeing the idea of גט get as
taking ownership over it. So then it says she never took ownership
over it. Whereas if the גט get was just an act of
giving it to her, you gave it to her. But there's another
way of framing it. The other way of framing it is why
is the yard considered her yard? The husband has the right of
פירות, peiros, okay, and he can actually void a sale that she
would do to the yard, and there's all these discussions of קניין
פירות כקניין הגוף דמי kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf dami or whatever. So
if it's on her person, you gave it to her. But why
is putting it on her yard giving it to her? The husband
has equal rights to that yard. Okay, so those are very different
ways of defining. Alright but קניין פירות כקניין הגוף kinyan peiros k'kinyan
haguf and he has rights to void it and we can have
the whole discussion, okay, and תוספות Tosafot discusses those issues. But at
least there's a very serious question to what degree are we prepared
to call it her yard. So therefore,
I'm sorry, you read the תוספות, Tosafot, okay. Anyway, the point is
that there are two ways of framing the question. One way of
framing the question is that the problem is that the husband gets
possession of the object, which then raises the question that you should
have asked it about when it's given to the woman herself as
well, תוספות Tosafot has a way of distinguishing those cases, but that
focuses on the idea of גט get as an aspect of קניין.
kinyan. The other is that the question is not that the husband
takes possession, but that it's the husband's yard... it's equally the husband's
yard and why is it considered like you gave it to the
woman? Why is putting it in her yard her yard? It's his
yard as well. So there's two ways of framing the question.
Okay, so how does it say חצירה? chatzeira?
That's the question.
What if he gives the yard as a gift?
Oh, so that's what תוספות Tosafot starts to ask. What if he's
given it... so if the issue is just the גט get meaning
on the condition... well what if he gives the yard as a
gift... meaning, if it's just a question that something that a woman
owns, the ownership transfers to the husband, you can walk around that.
You can say I'm giving it to you on the condition that
it doesn't transfer to the husband. The husband could give it to
her on condition that he doesn't get it back. So that would
seem an obvious answer,
which and also the point I was saying before, like then why
should it be different the yard or the hand? To me it's
much easier to read this question not the fact that the ownership
eventually gets back to the husband, which I think that there's a
lot of answers to, but the question is more like why is
the חצר chatzer considered her person, her property, if the husband has
rights to the חצר chatzer as well? Okay, so but yes, your
question is very apropos if the issue is not defining as giving
it to her, the issue is defining as who takes possession of
it because then there are ways to work around that, yes.
I understand how you laid it out. There's a landlord that owns
a shopping center and I've got a shop in the shopping center.
I'm a renter. I have plenty of rights to the space but
I don't own the real estate, the space. I have a landlord.
So she's his landlord in a way. She owns the principal of
the property.
No, but that's why I mentioned before. First of all, there's a
whole debate of קניין פירות כקניין הגוף. kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf. And
that might not be true. According to the position קניין פירות כקניין
הגוף, kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf, she's not considered the owner, he's basically
considered the owner, he has unlimited rights to the פירות, peiros, it's
not like it's a lease in a certain amount of time, he
has full use of it, so he might be considered to be
an owner. Number two, the Rabbis gave him special privileges. He can
void a sale that she makes on it. They made the... so
there's all these ways in which the husband's rights... like it's what
Michael's asking, I'm not going to get into this whole discussion, it's
a separate סוגיא, sukya, but there are all these ways in which
the husband's rights to the wife's property makes him consider possibly the
prime owner or an equal owner enough that you could say that
it's not fundamentally like he gave it to her. He's still... it's
like he gave it to her while he's still holding onto it
partly as well.
So there's two ways of framing the question.
Okay, distinguish between instructional things regarding the חצר chatzer itself, but whereas
traditional things regarding something that has nothing to do with the חצר,
chatzer, meaning like a גט. get. Then that's separate because there's But
if the idea is, if you start with the concept that you
have to give it to her person, ונתן בידה, unatan beyadah, and
you say that a חצר hatzer somehow is considered to be an
extension of her person, if you're not focusing on a קנין kinyan
idea, you're focusing on giving it to her and the חצר hatzer
is like a יד, yad, like an extension of her, so you
could say it's not fully an extension of her if he's got
his claws in that חצר hatzer as well. To me it makes
an enormous amount of sense. Why do you consider the חצר hatzer
like I gave it to her? You didn't put it... you didn't
give it to her away from you. You put it on some
property that you also have rights to. All right, let's move on.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Because because she has title to it
to when this distinction between his yard.
Right, but right,
but it's not really hers. I mean, he has all the rights
to it right now. She has title to it, but he has
all the rights. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, anyway that's two
ways of looking at this question. Okay, so אמר רב אלעזר, Amar
Rav Elazar, בכותב לה, bikhtov lah, דין ודברים אין לי בנכסייך. din
u'dvarim ein li benikhsayikh.
So he writes a document and says, I am waiving my rights
to your property. So that's going to be the question.
Okay, but somehow the גט get would make...
no, no, not in the גט, get, but before. But even there
it's going to be a question. So he basically has removed his
rights from the yard. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי כתב לה
הכי מאי הוי, v'ki katav lah hakhi mai havay, big deal? ותניא,
ve-tanya, אומר לחברו, omer le-chavero, דין ודברים אין לי על שדה זו,
din u'dvarim ein li al sadeh zu, ואין לי עסק בו, v'ein
li esek bo, ידי מסולקת הימנה. yadi mesuleket mimena.
Let's say somebody is a partner in a field, and then he
writes to his partner, I will have no claim against you regarding
this field and I have nothing to do with it and my
hands are removed from it, לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. All
that means nothing because he is saying that he doesn't have rights,
but it's not an issue of rights, it's an issue of ownership.
He's a part owner. If you want to give up your ownership,
you have to transfer your ownership. So you can't say, oh, I
am removing my rights from it. Rights is different than ownership. So
here too, if the husband wants to give up the פירות, peirot,
let him transfer the פירות peirot to the woman.
It's like making things הפקר hefker is giving up their ownership.
He didn't say that. He didn't say אני מפקיר מה שברשותי ani
mafkir mah she'bereshuti or whatever, my ownership. So מיגו דהפקר, migo d'hefker,
have to say the words הפקר? hefker? Oh, yeah, I mean
I don't know, it's an interesting question if you're trying to give
it to your... you're not making it הפקר hefker to the world,
you're trying to cede it to the other person.
Okay, so does rights when he gives the גט... get...
Okay, so we're going to get to that. Okay, anyway the גמרא
Gemara's question right now is a very technical one, which is saying
the phrase דין ודברים din u'dvarim is not enough for the husband
to get his... to cede his rights to the yard. So of
course the גמרא Gemara's answer could have been, so fine, he writes
it in the right way, give me a break. But anyway, אמי
דבי רבי ינאי, Ami d'bei Rabbi Yannai, so דבי רבנן d'bei Rabbanan
said בכותב לה ועודה ארוסה, bikhtov lah v'odah arusah, which is a
variation of it. No, no, no, before the נישואין. nissuin. Because he
only gets the rights to the yard at the נישואין. nissuin. That's
the field. That's only when he gets the פירות. peirot. So before
the נישואין nissuin he said, maybe he wrote like in the כתובה,
ketubah, I am waiving any of the rights I have to the
פירות peirot of the property that you are bringing in. So he
never got it in the first place, okay? He's refusing to receive
it at the time of the נישואין. nissuin. כי דרב כהנא, ki
d'Rav Kahana, like Rav Kahana says. דאמר רב כהנא, d'amar Rav Kahana,
נחלה הבאה לו לאדם ממקום אחר, nachlah haba'ah lo l'adam mimakom acher,
if something, an inheritance comes from somewhere else, meaning it's not like
a biblical case of inheritance. A child can't say, I am making
a claim that I will not inherit when my father dies. You
know, sorry, I mean that just happens automatically, you can't prevent that
from happening. Okay, but if it's coming from an external source, אדם
מתנה עליה שלא יירשנה, adam matneh alehah shelo yirshanah, he can make
a condition before it happens and saying that he's refusing to receive
it. וכדרבא, u'khideRava, like Rava says. דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava, האומר, ha-omer,
אי אפשי בתקנת חכמים, ee efshi b'takkanat chakhamim, if somebody will say,
make a say I refuse, I am not... I do not desire
the תקנה takkanah that the Rabbis made on my behalf, כגון זו
שומעין לו, k'gon zu shomin lo, you would listen. So here, for
example, the Rabbis said the husband is entitled to the fruit from
his wife's yard. So you cannot on a later say, oh, I
no longer want it, because once... once you get married, you actually
get a קנין kinyan in it. But before it takes effect, you
can make a claim that you refuse to accept that and then
that will work. One minute. כגון זו. kegon zu. מאי כגון זו?
mai kegon zu? What's like this? What was the original case of
saying that somebody can refuse the תקנת חכמים? takkanat chakhamim? כי דרב
הונא, ki d'Rav Huna, דאמר רב הונא, d'amar Rav Huna, דאמר רב.
d'amar Rav. דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav,
יכולה אשה שתאמר לבעלה. yakholah ishah shetomer l'ba'alah. A woman could say
to her husband, איני ניזונת ואיני עושה. eini nizonet v'eini osah. I
will not be supported by you, you don't pay my food bills,
and I won't work for you, and I don't... and you don't
get my labor. Now that, by the way, because we say that
the reciprocal things that are going on in the כתובה, ketubah, not
the פירות peirot of the... of the property, like of the dowry,
but the ongoing support that the husband gives the wife and then
the wife's labors for the husband and so on, that we say
was all done fundamentally to protect the woman's interests. It wasn't fundamentally
to give the husband rights to the wife's labor. It was fundamentally
to ensure that the woman would be provided for. And in exchange
for that, the husband gets her labor. So if she says, thank
you very much Rabbis, but actually I know you did this for
my interest and I am actually saying that it's more in my
interest not to be supported and to keep my own labor, then
we listen to her. That works. So a person can basically turn
down a תקנה takkanah of the Rabbis. Now that, interestingly, can be...
on an on-and-off basis. When they get married, you don't say it.
Then at a certain point, she's now making, you know, seven figures,
okay, and she's going to actually say, "You know what? I think
I'll keep my own salary and let him keep the פירות, peiros,
okay?" And then at another stage can actually say, "You know what?
I want to go back to the תקנת חכמים," takanas chachamim, okay,
because that's like an ongoing thing and there she can actually choose
to turn it on and turn it off and it's for her
benefit. The issue of קנין פירות kinyan peiros is differently—is different. The
issue of קנין פירות kinyan peiros is, once they come into the
marriage, she brings it in, he gets title or he gets an
actual קנין kinyan in the yard, in the field for the פירות.
peiros. So once he gets that, the only way he can reverse
it—no, no, no, if nothing was said beforehand. Once he gets that,
the only way he can reverse it is to say, "I מקנה
makneh it back to you." דין ודברים din u'dvarim won't work. But
before he gets it, he can make a protest and then he
will never get it. So that's the answer—no, he can. No, this
is done for him. The פירות, peiros, the פרנסה, parnassah, the food
and the מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim was done for her. This פירות
peiros was done for him. So here he can refuse, okay? So
the answer right now is, why when he puts it in her
yard is she מגורשת? megureshes? And it's that it's a special case
where he has basically prevented himself from getting קנין פירות kinyan peiros
in the yard. So it's a hundred percent her yard, he has
no rights to the yard, it's totally hers, it's an extension of
her, that's why it works. You had a question?
But you said it's not a דין ודברים, din u'dvarim, so just
trying to understand it.
If I say something about my חמץ, chametz, I don't say anything,
right? דין ודברים אין לי בחמץ זה? din u'dvarim ein li b'chametz
zeh? Right, presumably that...
חמץ chametz for Pesach? Well, no, because there's a whole question whether
חמץ chametz needs הפקר hefker either. לבטלו ולהוי כעפרא דארעא livatlei u'leihavei
k'afra d'ara is not language of הפקר hefker either. So there's a
whole discussion about חמץ. chametz. I don't want to get into it,
but by חמץ chametz you might not need real הפקר. hefker. חמץ
chametz actually it might be enough to say like I have no
interest in it.
But in terms of a business,
if you went ahead and you put your iPhone on this table
and you said "דין ודברים אין לי באייפון זו," din u'dvarim ein
li b'iPhone zu, that probably is not לשון הפקר, lashon hefker, correct?
It's still mine. Yeah, exactly. All right, so now let's see. Now
the גמרא Gemara continues. So answer number one is, it's a special
case that the husband does not have קנין פירות—does kinyan peiros not
have פירות—the peiros rights to פירות—in peiros the yard. He gave them
up or he never received them in the first place. רבא אמר,
Rava amar, רבא Rava says: אטו ידה
מי לא קניא ליה לבעל? atu yada mi lo kanya leh l'baal?
One minute, the husband also has rights to her hand, which means
what? Her labor, right? So why when he put it in her
hand is he actually putting it on property on her? It's also
his, the property as it were, you look at the hand as
property, he has his claws in that as well.
So what does she have to herself then, according to this way
of looking at it?
Nothing. Okay, what do you mean ever? When she gets divorced...
if her hand isn't hers, her yard isn't hers...
To the degree... okay, that's true while they're married. Welcome, okay. So
anyway, אלא גט וידה באים כאחד. ela get v'yadah ba'im k'echad. So
here's the point. As long as they're married, he has a קנין,
kinyan, he has rights to her labor, it's like her hand is
partly his. He has rights to her yard. But when they're divorced,
it's hers. So in the act of getting divorced, we sort of
see that once she is divorced this will be fully her
yard, once she is divorced this will be fully her hand, so
therefore it constitutes her hand and her yard during the act of
divorce. Okay?
It's simultaneous, it's coterminous.
Exactly, that's באים כאחד. ba'im k'echad. Yep.
הכא נמי, hacha nami, the same way that's true by her hand,
here true about the field. I keep on saying yard, it's a
field.
גט וחצרה באים כאחד—it git v'chatzeirah ba'im k'echad is חצר chatzer a
field, it is a yard. גט וחצרה באים כאחד. git v'chatzeirah ba'im
k'echad. אמר ליה
רבינא לרב אשי, amar leh Ravina l'Rav Ashi, רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי: Rav Ashi: רבא ידה דאשה קקשיא ליה? Rava yadah d'ishah
k'kashya leh? One minute, רבא Rava was bothered about the יד yad
of the woman and that was the basis for arguing that באים
כאחד ba'im k'echad and it works by the חצר. chatzer. One minute,
there's a big difference between a יד yad and a חצר. chatzer.
Okay, נהי דקני ליה למעשה ידיה ידה גופה מי קני ליה? nehi
d'kani leh l'ma'aseh yadeha yadah gufah mi kani leh? Yes, he has
rights to her labor, but it's not like he has a physical
ownership of the hand as her piece of his property, as opposed
to the field, the field you could really be talking about it
as a type of a property that she has title to but
he also has title to. But the hand, there's no question that
it's a type of a property that he owns. Now תוספות Tosafot
sharpens this, and תוספות Tosafot says for the reason that I said
a minute ago: that by the יד, yad, at any time she
could say "I'm going to keep my labor, you keep your פרנסה."
parnassah. What? Yeah.
So by the יד, yad, fundamentally it's in her control. She is
the one that gets to decide. She can say goodbye, you have
no longer rights to my labor, I'm keeping my labor, you keep
your פרנסה. parnassah. So that's why both because the יד yad isn't
property, it's her body, number one, and number two because she is
empowered to kick the husband off of her yard, as it were,
okay? So therefore the גמרא's Gemara saying, יד, yad, of course that's
her—her body, her yard—of course that she's considered... it's her, it's not
him. Okay, you got it? Because number one it's not property, and
number two because she can get him, she can remove his rights.
But the yard, it is property, she can't remove his rights, so
it still asks my question. How can you put it in yard?
That's still very much under his control at this moment. One minute,
let's see the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. ידה גופא מי קני ליה? Yadah
gufah mi kani leih? אמר להו רבא יד עבד קא קשיא ליה.
Amar lehu Rava yad eved ka kashya leih. No, no, no. רבא
Rava יד עבד קא קשיא ליה. yad eved ka kashya leih. רבא's
Rava proof that an idea of באים כאחד ba'im ke'echad was not
from the hand of the woman, it was from the hand of
a slave. למאן דאמר בשטר על ידי עצמו, Le-man de-amar bish'tar al
yedei atzmo, that you can free an עבד eved by giving him
a שטר, shtar, a writ of manumission directly to the עבד. eved.
So why did that work? יד עבד כיד רבו דמיא. Yad eved
ke-yad rabbo damya. The עבד, eved, a non-Jewish slave, an עבד כנעני,
eved Kena'ani, slave is considered property. So and and the slave does
not have any power there. So there his his hand is totally
the master's property. Why does it work to put it in the
slave's hands? אלא גיטו וידו באים כאחד. Ela gitto ve-yado ba'im ke'echad.
We must say by the case of the slave that since it's
an act of freeing him, it's in the context of that act
it's considered to be his own property and his own hand. הכא
נמי גיטו וחצירו באים כאחד. Hacha nami gitto va-chatzeiro ba'im ke'echad. Here
too. So that's רבא's Rava answer. So again, this סוגיא sugya I
think is best read not as the idea that when something gets
into the wife's חצר chatzeir it transfers ownership to the husband, because
there's ways of working around that. And the whole case of the
עבד eved shows you we're not really I think it's much more
as it's an act of giving it to her. Okay, her body
is her and even if he has rights it's still her body
and still her and he can get rid of those rights. But
why is the חצר chatzeir considered an extension of her if he
has rights to it? Okay, and there are two answers. One answer
is it's a special case where he doesn't have rights, he doesn't
have פירות. peirot. And the other is because we're looking one second
into the future and seeing what's going to happen as a result
of this act, and therefore that has the meaning in the context
of this act as well. Yes.
I I understand that the בעל Baal owns as it were the
body of the עבד כנעני. eved Kena'ani. Right. And the חידוש התורה
chiddush ha-Torah is if I injure that body which belongs to me,
right, I still have to pay compensation.
On what legal basis or rationale is that?
Well not compensation, he goes free.
He goes free, exactly. בשן ועין.
Be-shen va-ayin. Right.
But if not
then you don't pay compensation. But so what's the legal basis?
No actually do you I don't think mostly you don't
if I remembered correctly but mostly mostly right you own the body
of the yeah
well the תורה's Torah חידוש chiddush is is that at the same
time it's not denying the idea that an עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani
is property, it also recognizes the humanity of the person of the
of the עבד. eved. And the fact that the master could be
punished when he kills the עבד eved is a tremendous חידוש chiddush
of the תורה. Torah. Yeah right. So in other words it's but
it's not that it changes the definition of property. The very fact
that you don't pay the עבד eved that he goes free means
that as it and it's defined as a קנס knas not as
a compensation. That this was an act of this was an act
of brutality of cruelty that entitles the עבד eved to go free
but it's not a compensation issue.
But you couldn't apply like it's interesting that a similar logic is
not applied here.
Right because fundamentally the עבד eved is both property and he's a
human being so that's like the חידוש chiddush of the תורה Torah
that it doesn't ignore the fact that he's a human being. So
I understand. We're moving on. I got it. Okay wait wait just
let's move on hold on we got five minutes left. Okay. ההוא
שכיב מרע. Hahu shechiv meira. There was a person on his
deathbed דכתב לה גיטא לדביתהו. di-chesav lah gitta li-dveisahu. He wrote a
גט get to
his wife בהדי פניא דמעלי שבתא be-hadei panya de-ma'alei shabta on ערב
שבת. Erev Shabbos. ולא הספיק ומית ליה Ve-lo hispik u-meis leih and
he
didn't have a chance to give it to her. למחר תקיף ביה
עלמא. Le-machar takif beih alma. On שבת Shabbos he was
very very sick. It's clear he was about to die and he
needed to get her the גט get because he didn't want her
to have to deal with יבום. yibbum. Okay so what are you
gonna do on שבת? Shabbos? Now what's the problem? So give her
the darn גט. get. So you know the normal הלכה halacha is
is that you don't do קידושין kiddushin and גירושין gerushin on שבת.
Shabbos. But it's gonna be clear that the גמרא's Gemara not bothered
by that. And all the ראשונים Rishonim say well since we make
some accommodations for שכיב מרע shechiv meira anyway, we let him give
a deathbed bequest on שבת Shabbos and you're not supposed to do
קניינים kinyanim on שבת. Shabbos. And the reason for that is is
because we say that when he's on his deathbed you know we
want to do anything that will help his frame of mind. So
we're going to let him actually do גירושין gerushin on שבת Shabbos
as well. Okay you're going to let him do גירושין gerushin on
שבת Shabbos and that's what we're going to try to do. So
give her the darn גט. get. So everyone says well no the
גט get is מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay so let's take a look if
that's the reason. There's another answer I'll give you later. But seems
to be the way רש"י Rashi frames it here. The גט get
is he can do גירושין gerushin to calm his mind but we
have to somehow avoid the מוקצה muktzeh problem. So let's take a
look. אתו לקמיה דרבא. Asu le-kamei de-Rava. They came to רבא. Rava.
אמר להו רבא אילו אמרו ליה Amar lehu Rava ilu amru leih
say to the שכיב מרע shechiv meira לקנייה ניהלה לההוא דוכתא דיתיב
ביה גיטא. le-kanyeih nihalah le-hahu duchsah de-yasiv beih gitta.
Transfer ownership to the woman of the piece of property that the
גט get is on. That corner over there that the גט get
is on. ותיזיל ותיסגור ותיפתח, vesizil vesizgor vesiftach, let her go and
like lock the door, if it's in a closet let's say, and
open the door, so it's like a קניין חזקה, kinyan chazakah, ותיח
ותקנה vetach u'tekaneh and do a קניין חזקה kinyan chazakah on that
little space in the
closet, דתנן ותניא במתניתין, detnan utna b'mishnah, נעל גדר ופרץ, na'al gader
ufaratz, if somebody wants to take possession of land, what's חזקה chazakah
on land? You do something to improve the land. So if like
you lock the, you know, you lock the gate, or you make
a break in the gate if the gate needed to have an
opening there, כל שהוא לתיקונא הרי זו חזקה. kol shehu letikkuna harei
zu chazakah. By the way, it's a pretty big חידוש chiddush that
locking a door that's made to be closed and opened and locked
is considered חידוש chiddush by itself. I know. So that's a huge
חידוש chiddush by itself. But besides which, this is crazy! So you
should be with
מוקצה, muktzah, you're going to do a קניין kinyan on a piece
of property? So I mean it's like what's more feels like a...
I mean they're both דרבנן, derabbanan, but really? So the ר"ן's Ran
answer is well, but experientially it doesn't feel like a קניין kinyan
because experientially it just feels like you're opening and closing the closet
door, whereas מוקצה muktzah feels like you're actually, you know, doing something
wronger. That's the way... I don't, maybe. I mean once you say
go do a קניין kinyan on it, I don't know if experientially
to me that would frame it a lot. Anyway, that's the way
the ר"ן Ran explains it. But the שאילתות, She'iltos, I think it's
the שאילתות, She'iltos, has a different explanation. He says, what are you
talking about? Of course it was just a מוקצה muktzah problem, pick
up the darn גט get and give it to her. He says
the case is that the שכיב מרע shchiv mera is here and
the גט get is across the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim in another
place, in another house. So he can't give it to her. You
can't bring the גט get across רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and he's
sick, he's not going to get the גט. get. So that's the
problem. If it was just a מוקצה muktzah issue, of course just
give her the darn גט. get. All right? Anyway, so that one
way or another we can't move the גט get and this is
what had to be done. אמר ליה רב עיליש לרבא, Amar lei
Rav Ilish le-Rava, so רב עיליש Rav Ilish said to רבא, Rava,
מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה. mah she-kansah isha kanah ba'alah. I don't
understand, why did that work? The woman takes possession of the little
piece of the closet, but then that transfers ownership to the husband.
So she doesn't really own the closet. So you know she doesn't
own the little piece of floor that it was on. Okay. So
similar to the whole discussion before about פירות, peiros, איכסיף, ikhsif, he
was embarrassed. רבא Rava was.
ולסוף איגלאי מילתא דארוסה הוי. ulesof iglai milsa de-arusa hava. In the
end it turned out that she wasn't even a נשואה, nesua, she
was an
ארוסה. arusa. אמר רבא אם אמרו בנשואה יאמרו בארוסה? Amar Rava im
amru be-nesua yamru be-arusa? This idea מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה mah
she-kansah isha kanah ba'alah and קניין פירות kinyan peiros and all those
things then only kicks in at נישואין. nissuin. It's not true by
אירוסין. eirusin. So luckily the circumstances came together to mean that he
hadn't made a mistake. הדר אמר רבא, Hadar amar Rava, but then
רבא Rava said, you know what? Forget that. I was right the
first time. Like what, last time I thought I made a mistake,
I was wrong.
רבא רבא לא שנא ארוסה ולא שנא נשואה גיטה וחצרה באים כאחד.
Rava Rava lo shena arusa velo shena nesua gita vechatzerah ba'im ke'echad.
Her גט get and her חצר chatzer come at once. Now here's
a bigger חידוש chiddush a little bit because she's taking possession of
the חצר chatzer and the גט get and the, you know what
I'm saying? It's not like it was a חצר chatzer she already
had. But okay anyway,
so כאחד. ke'echad. והא אמר
רבא מעיקרא? veha amar Rava mei-ikara? No. Didn't רבא Rava already say
that? I mean at the top of the דף, daf, why was
he embarrassed? Why'd he have to go back? The גמרא Gemara says
no, מעיקרא, mei-ikara, I think it's מעיקרא mei-ikara is going on the
next line. מעיקרא כי אמר רבא האי מעשה אמרה. mei-ikara ki amar
Rava hai maisa amrah. No, actually this was the first case, this
was the first time רבא Rava said it. This story was the
origin of רבא Rava coming up with the idea of גיטה וידה
באים כאחד gita veyadah ba'im ke'echad so when we quoted it earlier
we were really quoting his conclusion that had emerged from this story.
Okay, we'll end with that for now.
There's an interesting bit of a time sequence.
Yeah, the time
saying you know like a 30 days extension to simultaneous. Right.
It's just a
even
though they could do it if you were making a diagram. Right.
It's an interesting sequence.
What do you mean? I'm missing your point.
Well we're talking about just previous to this...